<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Minimalism on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/tags/minimalism/</link><description>Recent content in Minimalism on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2024 16:49:59 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/tags/minimalism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The life-changing magic of tidying up: the Japanese art of decluttering and organizing</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/life-changing-magic/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 21:21:04 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/life-changing-magic/</guid><description>&lt;p>This book was my first real exposure to minimalism, and it completely changed how I feel about the possession of objects. It was super fortunate that my wife and I listened to it together on a road trip, and became equally enthralled with the idea of dumping all of our excess clutter.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="all-at-once">all at once &lt;a class="header-link" href="#all-at-once">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We have excess clutter because of a fundamental problem with the way we deal with possessions. This is difficult to solve with simple tricks like better organization or getting rid of one thing every day. She argues that the best way to overcome the clutter is by doing a one-time hardcore purge of the entire house. She spends a long time detailing what she calls the KonMari Method (which you can read about on her &lt;a href="https://konmari.com/what-is-konmari-method/">website&lt;/a>). For us, doing this initial purge took us about two weeks. We spent several hours each evening, plus all day on both Saturdays. All told I think we got rid of like 15 garbage bags-worth of things from our two-bedroom apartment.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>