<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>security on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/tags/security/</link><description>Recent content in security on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 18:28:49 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/tags/security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>hosting a Tor onion service</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/tor-onion-service/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 18:28:49 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/tor-onion-service/</guid><description>Tor onions are a way to host secure services that protect the anonymity of you and your clients. It also removes load from Tor exit nodes. If you open this page in the Tor browser it will redirect you to the following address:
http://kylrthjj7mpvktolz7u6fnudt3hpdvjw4hzquanjpepgsf5vcq5divad.onion/post/tor-onion-service/ which can only be opened from inside the Tor network.
getting started permalink To host an onion service, we&amp;rsquo;ll have a Docker container running Tor that decodes requests and forwards them to another container hosting the service.</description></item><item><title>using GPG to prove you wrote your code</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/gpg/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 07:13:54 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/gpg/</guid><description>GPG is cool. You can use GPG to send encrypted messages, sign files to prove you generated them, and sign git commits to prove you committed them. You can get my key here. DigitalOcean has a neat guide to getting started with GPG. It explains asymmetric encryption, key generation and revocation, and key signing and maintenance.
Git commit authorship can be modified by anyone, as demonstrated by this tool. But by uploading your GPG public key to GitHub, you allow anyone who trusts GitHub to be sure that commits marked &amp;ldquo;verified&amp;rdquo; were actually created by you.</description></item><item><title>using Matrix</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/matrix-registration/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 12:34:56 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/matrix-registration/</guid><description>Matrix is a federated, open source chat system. Federation means that people can message each other across different servers, like in the image below. In that way, it works sort of like email: even though you may use you@gmail.com and I might use me@kylrth.com, we can still write each other emails.
In our case, I host the server at matrix.kylrth.com, and you and I can connect to it with various clients.</description></item></channel></rss>