<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Health on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/tags/health/</link><description>Recent content in Health on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 10:03:08 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/tags/health/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Why we sleep: unlocking the power of sleep and dreams</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/why-we-sleep/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2023 22:00:32 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/why-we-sleep/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>There is &lt;a href="https://guzey.com/books/why-we-sleep/">controversy&lt;/a> around some of the claims made in this book, so I don&amp;rsquo;t take any single point of evidence extremely seriously. But the person who critiqued the book also has some weird ideas about sleep,&lt;span class="sidenote-number">&lt;small class="sidenote">For instance, he believes that we evolved in a sleep-deprived environment so sleep deprivation must be healthier for us.&lt;/small>&lt;/span>
so in the end I think I probably side with the sleep scientist for most issues except when he seems extreme. Isn&amp;rsquo;t epistemology fun?&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Being mortal: medicine and what matters in the end</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/being-mortal/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 09:04:11 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/being-mortal/</guid><description>&lt;p>Read this book before you turn 60. In fact, read it before you&amp;rsquo;re 40. Read it before your parents are 60. Read it if you have parents! Read it if you&amp;rsquo;re a person who is likely to die sometime in the future.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This book gave me tools for the hard decisions that exist for people in the last decade(s) of their lives. Before reaching this stage of life ourselves, we don&amp;rsquo;t think about it much because we&amp;rsquo;ve tended to separate the aged from our communities. We&amp;rsquo;ve lost a cultural understanding of what a good death looks like. This book brings that knowledge back to a world with modern medicine.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How not to diet: the groundbreaking science of healthy, permanent weight loss</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/how-not-to-diet/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 07:00:37 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/how-not-to-diet/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>I read this book with Irresistible and the Social Dilemma on my mind, so I have a lot of notes here about addiction and big business.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Just like everything else, capitalism has screwed over our diets by giving companies the incentive to put shareholders above customers. Food companies employ lobbyists to keep subsidies on sugar/corn syrup/meat, and keep a stranglehold on public organizations. They buy billions of dollars of ads to communicate the message that it&amp;rsquo;s laziness that has caused the obesity epidemic and to push their products that appeal to the unconscious desires of our brains to produce artificial hunger.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>