<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Matrix on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/tags/matrix/</link><description>Recent content in Matrix on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 16:26:59 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/tags/matrix/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Matrix setup with Synapse, Postgres, Maubot, and matrix-registration</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/matrix-setup/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 10:30:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/matrix-setup/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is how I set up my own &lt;a href="https://matrix.org">Matrix&lt;/a> server with Docker.&lt;span class="sidenote-number">&lt;small class="sidenote">These instructions were originally for ARM, back when I ran this server on a Raspberry Pi. Unfortunately, the Matrix community stopped releasing ARM images, so the latest version that will work on ARM without QEMU is v1.26.0, which is very old now. These instructions have been updated to use &lt;code>amd64&lt;/code> images, but I&amp;rsquo;ll preserve the references to ARM images as comments. If you&amp;rsquo;re going to work from a Pi, be sure to switch it to run in 64-bit mode for optimal performance: &lt;code>echo 'arm_64bit=1' | sudo tee -a /boot/config.txt &amp;amp;&amp;amp; sudo systemctl reboot&lt;/code>.&lt;/small>&lt;/span>
There is an &lt;a href="https://github.com/spantaleev/matrix-docker-ansible-deploy">Ansible playbook&lt;/a> that&amp;rsquo;s quite popular, but I host a lot of other services with Docker on the same server and I wanted to continue managing all of them together, just with &lt;code>docker-compose&lt;/code>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>using Matrix</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/matrix-registration/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 12:34:56 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/matrix-registration/</guid><description>&lt;p>Matrix is a &lt;em>federated&lt;/em>, open source chat system. Federation means that people can message each other across different servers, like in the image below. In that way, it works sort of like email: even though you may use &lt;code>you@gmail.com&lt;/code> and I might use &lt;code>me@kylrth.com&lt;/code>, we can still write each other emails.&lt;/p>
&lt;img src="federation.png" alt="using Matrix federation.png" class="img-zoomable">

&lt;p>In our case, I host the server at matrix.kylrth.com, and you and I can connect to it with various &lt;a href="https://matrix.org/ecosystem/clients/">clients&lt;/a>. We can write each other messages, but we can also communicate with people on other Matrix servers.&lt;span class="sidenote-number">&lt;small class="sidenote">There are a ton of cool features to Matrix, such as &lt;a href="https://matrix.org/bridges/">bridging&lt;/a>, voice and video calls, and encryption. You can read a more extensive beginner&amp;rsquo;s guide to Matrix &lt;a href="https://joinmatrix.org/">here&lt;/a>. Also check out the Matrix &lt;a href="https://matrix.org">website&lt;/a>.&lt;/small>&lt;/span>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>