<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lex-Fridman on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/tags/lex-fridman/</link><description>Recent content in Lex-Fridman on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2024 12:06:26 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/tags/lex-fridman/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>the inherent subjectivity of reality</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/edward-frenkel/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 14:45:44 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/edward-frenkel/</guid><description>These are some thoughts I&amp;rsquo;ve had while listening to a Lex Fridman interview with Edward Frenkel, a mathematician at UC Berkeley working on mathematical quantum physics.
In the information age, we like to see everything as computation. But what do we mean when we say that something is computation? We mean that a physical system with predictable interactions has a meaningful result. If we somehow learned that the universe was computational in nature, the only thing that adds is that the universe&amp;rsquo;s state is meaningful somehow.</description></item><item><title>ethics drift within bubbles</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/ethics-drift/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 08:35:54 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/ethics-drift/</guid><description>Here are some snippets from a Lex Fridman interview with John Abramson, outspoken critic of Big Pharma.
Lex: Are people corrupt? Are people malevolent? Are people ignorant that work at the low level and at the high level, at Pfizer for example? How is this possible? I believe that most people are good, and I actually believe if you join Big Pharma your life trajectory often involves dreaming, wanting, and enjoying helping people.</description></item><item><title>quotes from a Lex Fridman interview with Philip Goff</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/philip-goff/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 09:39:16 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/philip-goff/</guid><description>Here are some snippets from a Lex Fridman interview with Philip Goff, a panpsychist.
The Enlightenment ideal is to follow the evidence and the arguments where they lead, but it&amp;rsquo;s very hard for human beings to do that. I think we get stuck in some conception of how we think science ought to look. People talk about religion as a crutch, but I think a certain kind of scientism, a certain conception of how science is supposed to be, gets into people&amp;rsquo;s identity and their sense of themselves and their security.</description></item><item><title>meaning-making in the post-modern world</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/meaning-making/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 14:35:37 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/meaning-making/</guid><description>Here are some snippets from a Lex Fridman interview with Peter Wang, co-founder and CEO of Anaconda:
For a lot of human history, there wasn&amp;rsquo;t so much a meaning crisis as just a food and not getting eaten by bears crisis. Once you get to a point where you can make food there was a not getting killed by other humans crisis. Sitting around wondering what it&amp;rsquo;s all about is a relatively recent luxury.</description></item></channel></rss>