<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 13:19:47 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Team Human interview with Dennis Yi Tenen</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/team-human-tenen/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 10:34:12 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/team-human-tenen/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>You can view this episode &lt;a href="https://www.teamhuman.fm/episodes/265-dennis-yi-tenen">here&lt;/a>, and you can download a transcript I made with whisper-medium &lt;a href="https://dl.kylrth.com/teamhuman_tenen.txt">here&lt;/a>. I accept responsibility for errors in the transcript, alongside OpenAI, all people whose voices exist on the web, and the rest of humanity. :)&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="writing-technology">writing technology &lt;a class="header-link" href="#writing-technology">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>DYT&lt;/strong>: You know, it took humans like centuries to perfect the technology of a dictionary and it took hundreds, thousands of people, probably like millions of hours to actually get to the point where you can easily look up a word.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>thoughts on technology ownership</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/tech-ownership/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2023 12:11:06 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/tech-ownership/</guid><description>&lt;p>Having heard about the &lt;a href="https://foundation.mozilla.org/en/privacynotincluded/articles/its-official-cars-are-the-worst-product-category-we-have-ever-reviewed-for-privacy/">terrible privacy policies of car manufacturers&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/3/3/23624328/ford-self-repossessing-car-patent-connected-car-nightmare">Ford&amp;rsquo;s new patent to automate vehicle repossession&lt;/a>, I was finally able to formulate some thoughts I&amp;rsquo;ve had brewing for a while about ownership in this world of ubiquitous computing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Before the industrial revolution, humans could essentially understand what a thing did by looking at it, and ownership was about possession of the object. Now we don&amp;rsquo;t understand our tools, and so possession does not imply control.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>the NYT AI explainer misses the point</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/nyt-ai-explainer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2023 10:07:35 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/nyt-ai-explainer/</guid><description>&lt;p>In late March 2023, the NYT released a series of explainer articles about AI. The &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/article/ai-artificial-intelligence-chatbot.html">first article in the series&lt;/a>&lt;span class="sidenote-number">&lt;small class="sidenote">You can also &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20230415130643/https://www.nytimes.com/article/ai-artificial-intelligence-chatbot.html">read it on Archive.org&lt;/a> if you don&amp;rsquo;t have a subscription.&lt;/small>&lt;/span>
characterizes the recent history of AI as a progression of new technological ideas appearing over time. Of course that&amp;rsquo;s partially true, but it gets the order wrong and misses important non-technical events that are key to understanding our current position.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>the inherent subjectivity of reality</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/edward-frenkel/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 14:45:44 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/edward-frenkel/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>These are some thoughts I&amp;rsquo;ve had while listening to a Lex Fridman &lt;a href="https://lexfridman.com/edward-frenkel/">interview&lt;/a> with Edward Frenkel, a mathematician at UC Berkeley working on mathematical quantum physics.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the information age, we like to see everything as computation. But what do we mean when we say that something is computation? We mean that a physical system with predictable interactions has a meaningful result. If we somehow learned that the universe was computational in nature, the only thing that adds is that the universe&amp;rsquo;s state is meaningful somehow.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>for a socially beneficial and responsible development of AI</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/bengio-crawford/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 14:04:51 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/bengio-crawford/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>These are my notes from a conversation between &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yoshua_Bengio">Yoshua Bengio&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kate_Crawford">Kate Crawford&lt;/a> held at &lt;a href="https://mila.quebec/">Mila&lt;/a> on 2023-03-20, announcing the release of a new book created as a joint report between Mila and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UNESCO">UNESCO&lt;/a> called&lt;/em> Missing links in AI governance &lt;em>(&lt;a href="https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000384787">link&lt;/a>). There were news articles in French (&lt;a href="https://www.ledevoir.com/societe/785960/intelligence-artificielle-l-onu-et-le-mila-inquiets-des-derapages-potentiels-d-ia-comme-chatgpt">Le Devoir&lt;/a>), but not as many in English unfortunately (&lt;a href="https://www.datanami.com/this-just-in/mila-and-unesco-join-forces-to-emphasize-urgent-need-for-better-ai-governance/">Datanami&lt;/a>).&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Bengio&lt;/strong>: What motivates you to do what you do? This topic has turned from an academic move to a societal one really quickly, and it&amp;rsquo;s scary. We need to figure out what to do.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>the AI art debate</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/ai-art/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 12:09:25 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/ai-art/</guid><description>&lt;p>On 2022-11-03 a &lt;a href="https://githubcopilotlitigation.com/">class action lawsuit&lt;/a> was announced against GitHub Copilot on the basis of copyright infringement, and now (2023-01-13) there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20230114170709/https://stablediffusionlitigation.com/">one&lt;/a> for stable diffusion (against StabilityAI and friends). Browsing through r/StableDiffusion, I&amp;rsquo;m seeing lots of posts like &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/StableDiffusion/comments/10e13r3/the_lawyers_suing_stable_diffusion_when_you_tell/">this&lt;/a> making the very memeable point that 5 billion images can&amp;rsquo;t be stored in a 4 GB model. &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/StableDiffusion/comments/10e13r3/the_lawyers_suing_stable_diffusion_when_you_tell/j4oeny6/?context=3">From the original poster&lt;/a>:&lt;span class="sidenote-number">&lt;small class="sidenote">The thumbnail for this post was generated with stable diffusion. See the alt text for details. Yes, I&amp;rsquo;m not great at this.&lt;/small>&lt;/span>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>facts I've observed about how my brain stores knowledge</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/brain-knowledge/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2023 09:47:24 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/brain-knowledge/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m writing these things down over time because I&amp;rsquo;d like to figure out how to make artificial neural networks better at storing and retrieving knowledge, and the human brain is pretty good at that.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>When knowledge is new, it sometimes only comes back to me when I&amp;rsquo;m in the right context. For example, right now I can only think vaguely of how to adjust a chain derailleur on a bike, but I know that if I walked up to my bike and looked closely at the derailleur some more knowledge would appear. And we all have the familiar experience of being able to predict whether we&amp;rsquo;d recognize the name of a person or a song once it&amp;rsquo;s been said to us, but we can&amp;rsquo;t think of what it is until then.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>thoughts on Effective Altruism</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/effective-altruism/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 15:53:44 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/effective-altruism/</guid><description>&lt;p>Thanks to the crash of FTX and Scott Aaronson&amp;rsquo;s subsequent &lt;a href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6797">post&lt;/a> about SBF, I read a &lt;a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2022/08/15/the-reluctant-prophet-of-effective-altruism">very interesting deep-dive&lt;/a> into Effective Altruism by &lt;em>the New Yorker&lt;/em>. I&amp;rsquo;m seeing a lot of important characters show up that I&amp;rsquo;ve seen before: Eliezer Yudkowsky, earn-to-donate, 80,000 hours, etc. It&amp;rsquo;s really fascinating to see this all coming together in one narrative so I can understand a little better the inspiration for these ideas and the way that the movement has interacted with the world up till now. Here are my notes and critiques of the ethical ideas presented in the article.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>the effects of scale on worst-group performance</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/worst-group-scale/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2022 15:31:12 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/worst-group-scale/</guid><description>&lt;p>I think it&amp;rsquo;s valuable to be working in the open whenever possible, so I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep my research notes here. These notes will hopefully be full of good (and bad) ideas, so if someone borrows a good idea and publishes on it, that&amp;rsquo;s great!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This post contains my research notes as I try to understand how model scaling affects worst-group performance. This started as a group project in the neural scaling laws course at Mila in winter 2022. We presented about an existing &lt;a href="https://kylrth.com/paper/effect-of-model-size-on-worst-group-generalization/">paper&lt;/a> and presented our preliminary results &lt;a href="https://sites.google.com/view/nsl-course/schedule#h.o7ntdr3dzoiv">in class&lt;/a>. The repository for this project is &lt;a href="https://github.com/kylrth/worst_group_scale/">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>learning French</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/learning-french/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 12:19:08 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/learning-french/</guid><description>&lt;p>Here I&amp;rsquo;m going to document my efforts to learn French. I speak Spanish pretty well, which together with English gives me a strong base for comprehension.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>2021-08-01&lt;/strong>: I started using Duolingo every day, and got into the XP challenges to the point where I was getting like hundreds of points most days. I&amp;rsquo;ve currently (2022-06-01) got 15821 XP and 103 lesson crowns in the French course, and most of that came from Fall 2021. That really gave me a good sense for basic grammar and function words.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>WordBurner beta</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/wordburner/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2022 23:08:52 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/wordburner/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Update 2022-04-27&lt;/strong>: The beta is over, but the apk is still installable with the instructions below and any feedback sent from inside the app will be received by me. I&amp;rsquo;m going to be working on this more over the summer, and eventually publishing it on the app store. :)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ever since learning Spanish, it has been a dream of mine to create a vocabulary study app that meets my needs. Duolingo won&amp;rsquo;t cover advanced vocabulary, Anki requires manually-generated decks, and other apps have expensive subscription plans.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>ethics drift within bubbles</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/ethics-drift/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 08:35:54 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/ethics-drift/</guid><description>&lt;p>Here are some snippets from a Lex Fridman &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20221222002108/https://lexfridman.com/john-abramson/">interview&lt;/a> with John Abramson, outspoken critic of Big Pharma.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Lex&lt;/strong>: Are people corrupt? Are people malevolent? Are people ignorant that work at the low level and at the high level, at Pfizer for example? How is this possible? I believe that most people are good, and I actually believe if you join Big Pharma your life trajectory often involves dreaming, wanting, and enjoying helping people. And then we look at the outcomes that you&amp;rsquo;re describing and that&amp;rsquo;s why the narrative takes hold that Pfizer CEO Albert Bourla is malevolent. The sense is that these companies are evil. So if the different parts are people that are good and they want to do good, how are we getting these outcomes?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>notes about neuroscience</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/neuroscience/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 10:02:44 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/neuroscience/</guid><description>&lt;p>How much of brain structure is coded for in the genome? For example, the hippocampus is generally thought to be responsible for consolidating long-term memories. Is the specialization of this region an epigenetic phenomenon due to optimization in the environment, or is it coded more directly? Will we eventually see these structures emerge in artificial networks with sufficient scale and good optimization, or will we need to code it more directly?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>keep your tasks in the heap</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/tasks-stack-heap/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 11:23:20 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/tasks-stack-heap/</guid><description>&lt;p>Often when someone (usually a professor) is sharing their screen I see that their browser has so many tabs open that the descriptions are lost:&lt;/p>
&lt;img src="tabs.png" alt="keep your tasks in the heap tabs.png" class="img-zoomable">

&lt;p>That was my best impersonation as a Firefox user. Chrome will let you go a lot further (like ~113 tabs) before starting to provide a dropdown to show you the list of open tabs:&lt;/p>
&lt;img src="chrome_tabs.png" alt="keep your tasks in the heap chrome_tabs.png" class="img-zoomable">

&lt;p>Besides the obvious fact that this makes it hard to find a tab you&amp;rsquo;re looking for, you also waste computer memory and add to your cognitive load while you&amp;rsquo;re working.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>quotes from a Lex Fridman interview with Philip Goff</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/philip-goff/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 09:39:16 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/philip-goff/</guid><description>&lt;p>Here are some snippets from a Lex Fridman &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20221222002116/https://lexfridman.com/philip-goff/">interview&lt;/a> with Philip Goff, a panpsychist.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The Enlightenment ideal is to follow the evidence and the arguments where they lead, but it&amp;rsquo;s very hard for human beings to do that. I think we get stuck in some conception of how we think science ought to look. People talk about religion as a crutch, but I think a certain kind of scientism, a certain conception of how science is supposed to be, gets into people&amp;rsquo;s identity and their sense of themselves and their security.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>hosting a Tor onion service</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/tor-onion-service/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 18:28:49 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/tor-onion-service/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://community.torproject.org/onion-services/overview/">Tor onions&lt;/a> are a way to host secure services that protect the anonymity of you &lt;em>and&lt;/em> your clients. It also removes load from Tor exit nodes. If you open this page in the Tor browser it will redirect you to the following address:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-txt" data-lang="txt">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>http://kylrthjj7mpvktolz7u6fnudt3hpdvjw4hzquanjpepgsf5vcq5divad.onion/post/tor-onion-service/

&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>which can only be opened from inside the Tor network.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="getting-started">getting started &lt;a class="header-link" href="#getting-started">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To host an onion service, we&amp;rsquo;ll have a Docker container running Tor that decodes requests and forwards them to another container hosting the service. I&amp;rsquo;ve got a GitHub repo that will help you build the Tor image and shows you an example &lt;code>docker-compose.yml&lt;/code>:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>meaning-making in the post-modern world</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/meaning-making/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 14:35:37 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/meaning-making/</guid><description>&lt;p>Here are some snippets from a Lex Fridman &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20221227111818/https://lexfridman.com/peter-wang/">interview&lt;/a> with Peter Wang, co-founder and CEO of Anaconda:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>For a lot of human history, there wasn&amp;rsquo;t so much a meaning crisis as just a food and not getting eaten by bears crisis. Once you get to a point where you can make food there was a not getting killed by other humans crisis. Sitting around wondering what it&amp;rsquo;s all about is a relatively recent luxury.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>avatarify</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/avatarify/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2021 11:58:34 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/avatarify/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/alievk/avatarify-python">Avatarify&lt;/a> is a cool project that lets you create a relatively realistic avatar that you can use during video meetings. It works by creating a fake video input device and passing your video input through a neural network in PyTorch. My laptop doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a GPU, so I used the server/client setup.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="setting-up-the-server">setting up the server &lt;a class="header-link" href="#setting-up-the-server">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Be sure you&amp;rsquo;ve installed the Nvidia Docker runtime so that the Docker container can use the GPU. You can see how I did that &lt;a href="https://kylrth.com/post/jupyter-lab/">here&lt;/a>. Run the following on the server:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>hosting my own web services</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/self-hosting/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2021 07:57:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/self-hosting/</guid><description>&lt;img src="spaceship.jpg" alt="hosting my own web services spaceship.jpg" class="img-zoomable">

&lt;p>I host several services on an Alienware gaming computer I keep at my apartment. (We call it the spaceship.) I originally got the computer so I could have a computer with a GPU for machine learning projects, but I&amp;rsquo;ve since started using this computer to host a bunch of different services. Here I&amp;rsquo;ve documented how I set up the server.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="operating-system">operating system &lt;a class="header-link" href="#operating-system">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To keep things simple I use Ubuntu 20.04 LTS. Here&amp;rsquo;s a speedy way I&amp;rsquo;ve found to write installer ISOs to USB drives for installation:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>moving to Québec</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/qu%C3%A9bec/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 11:55:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/qu%C3%A9bec/</guid><description>&lt;p>We just moved our family from Utah, USA, to Montréal, Québec, Canada. I entered Canada on August 18, 2021 &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/maps/dir/Salt+Lake+City,+UT/montreal/@42.7334015,-101.7162703,5z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m13!4m12!1m5!1m1!1s0x87523d9488d131ed:0x5b53b7a0484d31ca!2m2!1d-111.8910474!2d40.7607793!1m5!1m1!1s0x4cc91a541c64b70d:0x654e3138211fefef!2m2!1d-73.567256!2d45.5016889">by car&lt;/a>, and my wife and daughter entered a few days later by air. The process actually began on April 27 when I got my acceptance letter to the Université de Montréal as a master&amp;rsquo;s student in the &lt;a href="https://diro.umontreal.ca/accueil/">Département d&amp;rsquo;informatique et de recherche opérationelle&lt;/a>. After a few days of scrambling to find out if I would be able to study there without knowing French (turns out you can as a grad student at DIRO!), I started the process of applying to enter Canada and live in Québec as a student.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Jupyter Lab Hub in Docker with Nvidia GPU support</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/jupyter-lab/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 20:28:25 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/jupyter-lab/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is how I set up my headless home server with a Jupyter Lab Docker container with an Nvidia GPU runtime. Login is handled by a GitHub OAuth application.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="nvidia-drivers-and-the-container-runtime">Nvidia drivers and the container runtime &lt;a class="header-link" href="#nvidia-drivers-and-the-container-runtime">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>First, check &lt;a href="https://docs.nvidia.com/cuda/archive/11.4.2/cuda-toolkit-release-notes/index.html">here&lt;/a> (replacing the CUDA version in the URL with your own) to see which Nvidia drivers you need for the CUDA toolkit version you want. I&amp;rsquo;m using CUDA 11.4.2, which means I need at least driver version 470.&lt;span class="sidenote-number">&lt;small class="sidenote">You can use &lt;code>sudo apt purge nvidia-*&lt;/code> to cleanly remove older drivers (or broken installs) before installing the desired version.&lt;/small>&lt;/span>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Minecraft in Docker</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/minecraft/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 13:25:28 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/minecraft/</guid><description>&lt;p>This guide shows how to host multiple Minecraft servers on a single machine with docker-compose.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-sh" data-lang="sh">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>mkdir minecraft_server
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>cd minecraft_server
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>mkdir data/
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>wget /post/minecraft/docker-compose.yml
 &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">\
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">&lt;/span> -O docker-compose.yml
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>This docker-compose setup uses itzg&amp;rsquo;s Docker image, which you see further documentation for &lt;a href="https://github.com/itzg/docker-minecraft-server">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re moving from a vanilla Minecraft world, do the following to get the different world directories in the right position:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-sh" data-lang="sh">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>cp -r &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">${&lt;/span>OLD&lt;span style="color:#e6db74">}&lt;/span>/world data/server/world
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>mkdir data/server/world_&lt;span style="color:#f92672">{&lt;/span>nether,the_end&lt;span style="color:#f92672">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>mv data/server/world/DIM-1 data/server/world_nether/DIM-1
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>mv data/server/world/DIM1 data/server/world_the_end/DIM1
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s the map from vanilla Minecraft directories to Spigot directories (which is what itzg&amp;rsquo;s container uses):&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Matrix setup with Synapse, Postgres, Maubot, and matrix-registration</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/matrix-setup/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 10:30:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/matrix-setup/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is how I set up my own &lt;a href="https://matrix.org">Matrix&lt;/a> server with Docker.&lt;span class="sidenote-number">&lt;small class="sidenote">These instructions were originally for ARM, back when I ran this server on a Raspberry Pi. Unfortunately, the Matrix community stopped releasing ARM images, so the latest version that will work on ARM without QEMU is v1.26.0, which is very old now. These instructions have been updated to use &lt;code>amd64&lt;/code> images, but I&amp;rsquo;ll preserve the references to ARM images as comments. If you&amp;rsquo;re going to work from a Pi, be sure to switch it to run in 64-bit mode for optimal performance: &lt;code>echo 'arm_64bit=1' | sudo tee -a /boot/config.txt &amp;amp;&amp;amp; sudo systemctl reboot&lt;/code>.&lt;/small>&lt;/span>
There is an &lt;a href="https://github.com/spantaleev/matrix-docker-ansible-deploy">Ansible playbook&lt;/a> that&amp;rsquo;s quite popular, but I host a lot of other services with Docker on the same server and I wanted to continue managing all of them together, just with &lt;code>docker-compose&lt;/code>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>I really just want to edit and compile my LaTeX files in VS Code</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/latex-vscode/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2021 21:43:47 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/latex-vscode/</guid><description>&lt;p>LaTeX has a ton of different flavors, releases, and installations: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MacTeX">MacTeX&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MiKTeX">MiKTeX&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TeXworks">TeXworks&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XeTeX">XeTeX&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PdfTeX">pdfTeX&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LuaTeX">LuaTeX&lt;/a>&amp;hellip; If you&amp;rsquo;re using Linux and just want to edit LaTeX files in Visual Studio Code and have them automatically rendered as PDFs, follow these instructions:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>On Arch-based distros, install the packages listed &lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/TeX_Live">here&lt;/a>. On Debian-based systems, &lt;code>sudo apt install texlive&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Install some Perl dependencies:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>sudo cpan Log::Log4perl Log::LogDispatch Log::Dispatch::File YAML::Tiny File::HomeDir
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>If you want to use FontAwesome on Arch-based systems, install the &lt;code>oft-font-awesome&lt;/code> package and then do the following (&lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/TeX_Live#Making_fonts_available_to_Fontconfig">source&lt;/a>):&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>using GPG to prove you wrote your code</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/gpg/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 07:13:54 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/gpg/</guid><description>&lt;p>GPG is cool. You can use GPG to send encrypted messages, sign files to prove you generated them, and sign git commits to prove you committed them. You can get my key &lt;a href="https://kylrth.com/gpg.pub">here&lt;/a>. DigitalOcean has a &lt;a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/how-to-use-gpg-to-encrypt-and-sign-messages">neat guide&lt;/a> to getting started with GPG. It explains asymmetric encryption, key generation and revocation, and key signing and maintenance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Git commit authorship can be modified by anyone, as demonstrated by &lt;a href="https://github.com/jayphelps/git-blame-someone-else">this tool&lt;/a>. But by uploading your GPG public key to GitHub, you allow anyone who trusts GitHub to be sure that commits marked &amp;ldquo;verified&amp;rdquo; were actually created by you.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>favorite art</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/art/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2021 22:16:52 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/art/</guid><description>&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s some of my favorite art.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="edvard-munch-the-scream-1893">Edvard Munch, &lt;em>The Scream&lt;/em>, 1893 &lt;a class="header-link" href="#edvard-munch-the-scream-1893">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;img src="scream.jpg" alt="favorite art scream.jpg" class="img-zoomable">

&lt;p>(&lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Edvard_Munch,_1893,_The_Scream,_oil,_tempera_and_pastel_on_cardboard,_91_x_73_cm,_National_Gallery_of_Norway.jpg">source&lt;/a>)&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="ben-shahn-all-that-is-beautiful-1966">Ben Shahn, &lt;em>All That Is Beautiful&lt;/em>, 1966 &lt;a class="header-link" href="#ben-shahn-all-that-is-beautiful-1966">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;img src="all_that_is_beautiful.jpg" alt="favorite art all_that_is_beautiful.jpg" class="img-zoomable">

&lt;p>(&lt;a href="https://americanart.si.edu/artwork/all-beautiful-22167">source&lt;/a>)&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="peter-doig-architect-1991">Peter Doig, &lt;em>Architect&amp;rsquo;s Home in the Ravine&lt;/em>, 1991 &lt;a class="header-link" href="#peter-doig-architect-1991">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;img src="architect_home_in_the_ravine.jpg" alt="favorite art architect_home_in_the_ravine.jpg" class="img-zoomable">

&lt;p>(&lt;a href="https://www.wikiart.org/en/peter-doig/architect-s-home-in-the-ravine-1991">source&lt;/a>)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Removing a keyword from git history</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/removing-keyword-from-git-history/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 11:34:25 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/removing-keyword-from-git-history/</guid><description>&lt;p>I recently had to remove a keyword from the git history of a project I was working on. This meant not just &lt;a href="https://docs.github.com/en/free-pro-team@latest/github/authenticating-to-github/removing-sensitive-data-from-a-repository#using-filter-branch">removing a file&lt;/a> but modifying commits where the keyword was added, commits where the keyword was removed, and even commits with the keyword in the commit message. I eventually came to the right solution through a mix of blog posts and the documentation for &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/git-rebase/">&lt;code>git rebase&lt;/code>&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For this example, assume the keyword is &amp;ldquo;matrix&amp;rdquo;. The example output shown is from the git repo for this website.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>using Matrix</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/matrix-registration/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 12:34:56 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/matrix-registration/</guid><description>&lt;p>Matrix is a &lt;em>federated&lt;/em>, open source chat system. Federation means that people can message each other across different servers, like in the image below. In that way, it works sort of like email: even though you may use &lt;code>you@gmail.com&lt;/code> and I might use &lt;code>me@kylrth.com&lt;/code>, we can still write each other emails.&lt;/p>
&lt;img src="federation.png" alt="using Matrix federation.png" class="img-zoomable">

&lt;p>In our case, I host the server at matrix.kylrth.com, and you and I can connect to it with various &lt;a href="https://matrix.org/ecosystem/clients/">clients&lt;/a>. We can write each other messages, but we can also communicate with people on other Matrix servers.&lt;span class="sidenote-number">&lt;small class="sidenote">There are a ton of cool features to Matrix, such as &lt;a href="https://matrix.org/bridges/">bridging&lt;/a>, voice and video calls, and encryption. You can read a more extensive beginner&amp;rsquo;s guide to Matrix &lt;a href="https://joinmatrix.org/">here&lt;/a>. Also check out the Matrix &lt;a href="https://matrix.org">website&lt;/a>.&lt;/small>&lt;/span>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>