<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>technology on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/tags/technology/</link><description>Recent content in technology on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2023 12:11:06 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/tags/technology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>thoughts on technology ownership</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/tech-ownership/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2023 12:11:06 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/tech-ownership/</guid><description>Having heard about the terrible privacy policies of car manufacturers and Ford&amp;rsquo;s new patent to automate vehicle repossession, I was finally able to formulate some thoughts I&amp;rsquo;ve had brewing for a while about ownership in this world of ubiquitous computing.
Before the industrial revolution, humans could essentially understand what a thing did by looking at it, and ownership was about possession of the object. Now we don&amp;rsquo;t understand our tools, and so possession does not imply control.</description></item><item><title>Tools and weapons: the promise and peril of the digital age</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/tools-and-weapons/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 20:58:02 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/tools-and-weapons/</guid><description>I started taking notes later in the book. There were lots of good insights in the first half. Sorry!
broadband access permalink Getting the internet to rural communities is a big deal for the rural economy. Just like electricity, it&amp;rsquo;s something that needs government support because there isn&amp;rsquo;t the economic incentive for ISPs to reach some of these locations.
ethical AI permalink The focus on AI now is not just a fad, but a convergence of several trends that have made AI the next logical step: the increased computational resources, flexible access to compute through the cloud, etc.</description></item></channel></rss>