<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>History on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/tags/history/</link><description>Recent content in History on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 13:19:47 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/tags/history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The right side of history: how reason and moral purpose made the West great</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/right-side-of-history/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 13:36:03 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/right-side-of-history/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The main text below is my summary of the points in the book, and I&amp;rsquo;ve put my commentary in sidenotes. If you want a Marxist, postmodern response to these ideas from the devil himself, check out&lt;/em> &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SEMB1Ky2n1E">Jordan Peterson &amp;amp; the meaning of life&lt;/a> &lt;em>by Philosophy Tube.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Reason and moral purpose come from Athens and Jerusalem, and without those things the West would not be where it is today. Socialism means taking handouts from the nanny state, and while our society continues to function with capitalism bearing the weight of socialist programs, it&amp;rsquo;s in the process of crumbling. People on the left like to blame institutions and systems for current woes, when in reality this is the freest, most egalitarian society that has ever existed. That&amp;rsquo;s why we see the conflict over political divides strengthening in America. The West is losing its attachment to reason and moral purpose, instead shifting to intersectionality, hedonism, and scientific materialism. Happiness is built on a sense of moral purpose, and is achieved by maximizing individuals&amp;rsquo; ability to &lt;em>pursue&lt;/em> that happiness. Scientific materialism and atheism are problematic because they take away that moral purpose.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A short history of nearly everything</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/short-history-nearly-everything/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2020 11:19:03 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/short-history-nearly-everything/</guid><description>&lt;p>We are &lt;em>extremely&lt;/em> lucky to be here, and even more lucky to be able to appreciate it. Let&amp;rsquo;s not waste it.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>