<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Politics on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/tags/politics/</link><description>Recent content in Politics on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 16:26:59 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/tags/politics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Thinking in systems: a primer</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/thinking-in-systems/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 11:17:09 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/thinking-in-systems/</guid><description>&lt;p>A system is something that is composed of parts that have interrelations between them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Each system has purposes, and those purposes may have nothing to do with stated goals. For example, if a government says it wants to protect the environment but allocates few resources to that goal, its purpose is not to protect the environment, but something else. A university may have the purpose of teaching students, while the components of the university have different goals: the student is trying to get good grades, the professor is trying to produce good research, and the administrator is trying to balance the budget.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bowling alone: the collapse and revival of American community</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/bowling-alone/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 10:36:57 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/bowling-alone/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-trends">the trends &lt;a class="header-link" href="#the-trends">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>politics&lt;/strong>: There is now more money in politics, and less individual involvement. There are more total associations, but they look more like the AARP and Greenpeace, instead of unions, churches, bridge clubs, rotary.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>religion&lt;/strong>: Attendance has definitely gone down in the last 40 years, even if the number of people who profess stays nearly the same. (This has changed since the book was published on January 1, 2000.) The 60s and 70s saw people make their religion more private, more personal, making people less concerned with the communal support of a shared faith. Fundamentalist religion (including evangelical) results in more service and giving, but primarily within the church community. So as the mainline middle falls out, religion is becoming a less helpful societal lubricant overall, despite the fact that religiosity has generally meant more volunteerism and giving.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Better, Nicer, Clearer, Fairer: a critical assessment of the movement for ethical artificial intelligence and machine learning</title><link>https://kylrth.com/paper/better-nicer-cleaner-fairer/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2023 12:53:31 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/paper/better-nicer-cleaner-fairer/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>I will present this paper in the FATE (fairness, accountability, transparency, ethics) reading group tomorrow (2023-10-25). You can view the slides I&amp;rsquo;ll use &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1Bl4Bfh-ryFfmsEVrmdnYBe69hKjZP4mYZppvZHU5-yM/edit?usp=sharing">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are unresolved tensions in the algorithmic ethics world. Here are two examples:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Is inclusion always good?
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Gebru: &amp;ldquo;you can&amp;rsquo;t have ethical A.I. that&amp;rsquo;s not inclusive&amp;hellip; [a]nd whoever is creating the technology is setting the standards&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nelson: &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip; I struggle to understand why we want to make black communities more cognizant in facial recognition systems that are disproportionately used for surveillance.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>academic activism
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>O&amp;rsquo;Neil: why is there a lack of academic efforts to inform policymakers and regulators?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>PERVADE: Academics have been doing this work for a while but it is underfunded, marginalized, and at odds with a US political apparatus generally favorable towards Silicon Valley.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Ethics manifestos or value statements mask these tensions behind a business ethics lens.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The right side of history: how reason and moral purpose made the West great</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/right-side-of-history/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 13:36:03 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/right-side-of-history/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The main text below is my summary of the points in the book, and I&amp;rsquo;ve put my commentary in sidenotes. If you want a Marxist, postmodern response to these ideas from the devil himself, check out&lt;/em> &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SEMB1Ky2n1E">Jordan Peterson &amp;amp; the meaning of life&lt;/a> &lt;em>by Philosophy Tube.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Reason and moral purpose come from Athens and Jerusalem, and without those things the West would not be where it is today. Socialism means taking handouts from the nanny state, and while our society continues to function with capitalism bearing the weight of socialist programs, it&amp;rsquo;s in the process of crumbling. People on the left like to blame institutions and systems for current woes, when in reality this is the freest, most egalitarian society that has ever existed. That&amp;rsquo;s why we see the conflict over political divides strengthening in America. The West is losing its attachment to reason and moral purpose, instead shifting to intersectionality, hedonism, and scientific materialism. Happiness is built on a sense of moral purpose, and is achieved by maximizing individuals&amp;rsquo; ability to &lt;em>pursue&lt;/em> that happiness. Scientific materialism and atheism are problematic because they take away that moral purpose.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Team Human interview with Dennis Yi Tenen</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/team-human-tenen/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 10:34:12 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/team-human-tenen/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>You can view this episode &lt;a href="https://www.teamhuman.fm/episodes/265-dennis-yi-tenen">here&lt;/a>, and you can download a transcript I made with whisper-medium &lt;a href="https://dl.kylrth.com/teamhuman_tenen.txt">here&lt;/a>. I accept responsibility for errors in the transcript, alongside OpenAI, all people whose voices exist on the web, and the rest of humanity. :)&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="writing-technology">writing technology &lt;a class="header-link" href="#writing-technology">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>DYT&lt;/strong>: You know, it took humans like centuries to perfect the technology of a dictionary and it took hundreds, thousands of people, probably like millions of hours to actually get to the point where you can easily look up a word.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>thoughts on technology ownership</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/tech-ownership/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2023 12:11:06 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/tech-ownership/</guid><description>&lt;p>Having heard about the &lt;a href="https://foundation.mozilla.org/en/privacynotincluded/articles/its-official-cars-are-the-worst-product-category-we-have-ever-reviewed-for-privacy/">terrible privacy policies of car manufacturers&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/3/3/23624328/ford-self-repossessing-car-patent-connected-car-nightmare">Ford&amp;rsquo;s new patent to automate vehicle repossession&lt;/a>, I was finally able to formulate some thoughts I&amp;rsquo;ve had brewing for a while about ownership in this world of ubiquitous computing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Before the industrial revolution, humans could essentially understand what a thing did by looking at it, and ownership was about possession of the object. Now we don&amp;rsquo;t understand our tools, and so possession does not imply control.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>the NYT AI explainer misses the point</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/nyt-ai-explainer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2023 10:07:35 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/nyt-ai-explainer/</guid><description>&lt;p>In late March 2023, the NYT released a series of explainer articles about AI. The &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/article/ai-artificial-intelligence-chatbot.html">first article in the series&lt;/a>&lt;span class="sidenote-number">&lt;small class="sidenote">You can also &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20230415130643/https://www.nytimes.com/article/ai-artificial-intelligence-chatbot.html">read it on Archive.org&lt;/a> if you don&amp;rsquo;t have a subscription.&lt;/small>&lt;/span>
characterizes the recent history of AI as a progression of new technological ideas appearing over time. Of course that&amp;rsquo;s partially true, but it gets the order wrong and misses important non-technical events that are key to understanding our current position.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Winners take all: the elite charade of changing the world</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/winners-take-all/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 14:48:27 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/winners-take-all/</guid><description>&lt;p>This book was a good one for quotable critique of modern capitalism. Here are some good ones:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>These elites believe and promote the idea that social change should be pursued principally through the free market and voluntary action, not public life and the law and the reform of the systems that people share in common; that it should be supervised by the winners of capitalism and their allies, and not be antagonistic to their needs; and that the biggest beneficiaries of the status quo should play a leading role in the status quo’s reform.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Army of none: autonomous weapons and the future of war</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/army-of-none/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 13:33:19 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/army-of-none/</guid><description>&lt;p>The examples in this book make it clear that there is no easy line we can draw between autonomous and non-autonomous weapons (and by extension, autonomous AI agents). There is a smooth gradient of autonomy, which makes the question of allowing autonomous weapons much more nuanced. It&amp;rsquo;s probably the case that higher-level alignment becomes important proportionally to the level of autonomy and intelligence.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He analyzes the Patriot fratricides,&lt;span class="sidenote-number">&lt;small class="sidenote">In a military context, the word &lt;em>fratricide&lt;/em> means the killing of someone on the same side of a conflict.&lt;/small>&lt;/span>
and ends up blaming the individuals involved for automation bias. I would say that these humans in the system were set up to fail by the training and the functioning of the system. They&amp;rsquo;re expected to decide whether the computer is right, with only seconds to decide. He acknowledges this later when he talks about Aegis.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The big three in economics: Adam Smith, Karl Marx, and John Maynard Keynes</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/big-three-economics/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 13:28:01 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/big-three-economics/</guid><description>&lt;p>This book was published in 2007, before the Great Recession. It definitely reads that way. Very capitalist, very Christian, very neo-liberal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I enjoyed learning more about Adam Smith. I feel like Skousen does a good job painting the importance of his ideas as an invention that drove the Industrial Revolution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to Skousen, Marx is the devil incarnate, and his ideas are a dangerous disease infecting the minds of intellectuals and workers. Skousen takes a strange interest in painting Marx and Keynes as deranged, sexual deviants, etc. (&amp;ldquo;The Truth about Keynes&amp;rsquo; Homosexuality&amp;rdquo; is a section in this book.)&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>