<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Policy on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/tags/policy/</link><description>Recent content in Policy on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2024 16:49:59 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/tags/policy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Experienced well-being rises with income, even above $75,000 per year</title><link>https://kylrth.com/paper/experienced-well-being/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2022 13:34:53 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/paper/experienced-well-being/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Turns out that money does buy happiness.&lt;/strong> You may have heard that people&amp;rsquo;s average happiness stops improving once you make more than $75,000/year? Researchers did a better survey with more data and found that that was not the case.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The researchers cited 5 methodological improvements over the old research that suggested that it didn&amp;rsquo;t matter after $75,000:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>They measured people&amp;rsquo;s happiness in real time, instead of having people try to remember past happiness levels.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>They measured on a continuous scale instead of discrete. (The survey had a slider between &amp;ldquo;very bad&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;very good&amp;rdquo;, instead of discrete options to choose from.)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>They measured on &amp;ldquo;dozens of separate occasions per person&amp;rdquo; using an app, instead of just a single questionnaire.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>They used a comparable scale for experienced well-being (people’s evaluations of their lives) and evaluative well-being (how people feel during the day-to-day moments of their lives).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>They included a large number of high-earning participants and measured higher incomes in more granular increments.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The data were collected from 33,391 employed adults (ages 18-65) in the United States. There were a total of 1,725,994 reports collected, so that&amp;rsquo;s ~52 reports per person.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>