<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Philosophy on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/tags/philosophy/</link><description>Recent content in Philosophy on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 10:03:08 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/tags/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The right side of history: how reason and moral purpose made the West great</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/right-side-of-history/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 13:36:03 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/right-side-of-history/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The main text below is my summary of the points in the book, and I&amp;rsquo;ve put my commentary in sidenotes. If you want a Marxist, postmodern response to these ideas from the devil himself, check out&lt;/em> &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SEMB1Ky2n1E">Jordan Peterson &amp;amp; the meaning of life&lt;/a> &lt;em>by Philosophy Tube.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Reason and moral purpose come from Athens and Jerusalem, and without those things the West would not be where it is today. Socialism means taking handouts from the nanny state, and while our society continues to function with capitalism bearing the weight of socialist programs, it&amp;rsquo;s in the process of crumbling. People on the left like to blame institutions and systems for current woes, when in reality this is the freest, most egalitarian society that has ever existed. That&amp;rsquo;s why we see the conflict over political divides strengthening in America. The West is losing its attachment to reason and moral purpose, instead shifting to intersectionality, hedonism, and scientific materialism. Happiness is built on a sense of moral purpose, and is achieved by maximizing individuals&amp;rsquo; ability to &lt;em>pursue&lt;/em> that happiness. Scientific materialism and atheism are problematic because they take away that moral purpose.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>the inherent subjectivity of reality</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/edward-frenkel/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 14:45:44 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/edward-frenkel/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>These are some thoughts I&amp;rsquo;ve had while listening to a Lex Fridman &lt;a href="https://lexfridman.com/edward-frenkel/">interview&lt;/a> with Edward Frenkel, a mathematician at UC Berkeley working on mathematical quantum physics.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the information age, we like to see everything as computation. But what do we mean when we say that something is computation? We mean that a physical system with predictable interactions has a meaningful result. If we somehow learned that the universe was computational in nature, the only thing that adds is that the universe&amp;rsquo;s state is meaningful somehow.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>the AI art debate</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/ai-art/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 12:09:25 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/ai-art/</guid><description>&lt;p>On 2022-11-03 a &lt;a href="https://githubcopilotlitigation.com/">class action lawsuit&lt;/a> was announced against GitHub Copilot on the basis of copyright infringement, and now (2023-01-13) there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://stablediffusionlitigation.com/">one&lt;/a> for stable diffusion (against StabilityAI and friends). Browsing through r/StableDiffusion, I&amp;rsquo;m seeing lots of posts like &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/StableDiffusion/comments/10e13r3/the_lawyers_suing_stable_diffusion_when_you_tell/">this&lt;/a> making the very memeable point that 5 billion images can&amp;rsquo;t be stored in a 4 GB model. &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/StableDiffusion/comments/10e13r3/the_lawyers_suing_stable_diffusion_when_you_tell/j4oeny6/?context=3">From the original poster&lt;/a>:&lt;span class="sidenote-number">&lt;small class="sidenote">The thumbnail for this post was generated with stable diffusion. See the alt text for details. Yes, I&amp;rsquo;m not great at this.&lt;/small>&lt;/span>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Conscious: a brief guide to the fundamental mystery of the mind</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/conscious/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 16:57:49 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/conscious/</guid><description>&lt;p>The first thing you should know is that this book is only 2 hours long in audio form. That&amp;rsquo;s short! She managed to get into the difficult details while keeping the jargon accessible. (It helps that we literally know nothing about consciousness.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This book argued alternately for neuroscientific, illusionist, and panpsychist theories of consciousness. It explains the hard problem of consciousness, and then later &lt;em>really&lt;/em> explains why it&amp;rsquo;s so hard. As a science-oriented person, t&amp;rsquo;s so easy to forget why it&amp;rsquo;s hard and start to explain things purely physically. When I do that, I end up thinking there&amp;rsquo;s got to be a neuroscience explanation. When I pay attention once again to my own experience, I lean towards some kind of panpsychism. The author really lays bare her own thoughts, and carefully spends time walking us through simple thought experiments to fight off the assumptions that we bring to the word &amp;ldquo;consciousness&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Being mortal: medicine and what matters in the end</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/being-mortal/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 09:04:11 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/being-mortal/</guid><description>&lt;p>Read this book before you turn 60. In fact, read it before you&amp;rsquo;re 40. Read it before your parents are 60. Read it if you have parents! Read it if you&amp;rsquo;re a person who is likely to die sometime in the future.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This book gave me tools for the hard decisions that exist for people in the last decade(s) of their lives. Before reaching this stage of life ourselves, we don&amp;rsquo;t think about it much because we&amp;rsquo;ve tended to separate the aged from our communities. We&amp;rsquo;ve lost a cultural understanding of what a good death looks like. This book brings that knowledge back to a world with modern medicine.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The big three in economics: Adam Smith, Karl Marx, and John Maynard Keynes</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/big-three-economics/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 13:28:01 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/big-three-economics/</guid><description>&lt;p>This book was published in 2007, before the Great Recession. It definitely reads that way. Very capitalist, very Christian, very neo-liberal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I enjoyed learning more about Adam Smith. I feel like Skousen does a good job painting the importance of his ideas as an invention that drove the Industrial Revolution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to Skousen, Marx is the devil incarnate, and his ideas are a dangerous disease infecting the minds of intellectuals and workers. Skousen takes a strange interest in painting Marx and Keynes as deranged, sexual deviants, etc. (&amp;ldquo;The Truth about Keynes&amp;rsquo; Homosexuality&amp;rdquo; is a section in this book.)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>thoughts on Effective Altruism</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/effective-altruism/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 15:53:44 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/effective-altruism/</guid><description>&lt;p>Thanks to the crash of FTX and Scott Aaronson&amp;rsquo;s subsequent &lt;a href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6797">post&lt;/a> about SBF, I read a &lt;a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2022/08/15/the-reluctant-prophet-of-effective-altruism">very interesting deep-dive&lt;/a> into Effective Altruism by &lt;em>the New Yorker&lt;/em>. I&amp;rsquo;m seeing a lot of important characters show up that I&amp;rsquo;ve seen before: Eliezer Yudkowsky, earn-to-donate, 80,000 hours, etc. It&amp;rsquo;s really fascinating to see this all coming together in one narrative so I can understand a little better the inspiration for these ideas and the way that the movement has interacted with the world up till now. Here are my notes and critiques of the ethical ideas presented in the article.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>ethics drift within bubbles</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/ethics-drift/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 08:35:54 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/ethics-drift/</guid><description>&lt;p>Here are some snippets from a Lex Fridman &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20221222002108/https://lexfridman.com/john-abramson/">interview&lt;/a> with John Abramson, outspoken critic of Big Pharma.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Lex&lt;/strong>: Are people corrupt? Are people malevolent? Are people ignorant that work at the low level and at the high level, at Pfizer for example? How is this possible? I believe that most people are good, and I actually believe if you join Big Pharma your life trajectory often involves dreaming, wanting, and enjoying helping people. And then we look at the outcomes that you&amp;rsquo;re describing and that&amp;rsquo;s why the narrative takes hold that Pfizer CEO Albert Bourla is malevolent. The sense is that these companies are evil. So if the different parts are people that are good and they want to do good, how are we getting these outcomes?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Experienced well-being rises with income, even above $75,000 per year</title><link>https://kylrth.com/paper/experienced-well-being/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2022 13:34:53 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/paper/experienced-well-being/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Turns out that money does buy happiness.&lt;/strong> You may have heard that people&amp;rsquo;s average happiness stops improving once you make more than $75,000/year? Researchers did a better survey with more data and found that that was not the case.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The researchers cited 5 methodological improvements over the old research that suggested that it didn&amp;rsquo;t matter after $75,000:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>They measured people&amp;rsquo;s happiness in real time, instead of having people try to remember past happiness levels.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>They measured on a continuous scale instead of discrete. (The survey had a slider between &amp;ldquo;very bad&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;very good&amp;rdquo;, instead of discrete options to choose from.)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>They measured on &amp;ldquo;dozens of separate occasions per person&amp;rdquo; using an app, instead of just a single questionnaire.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>They used a comparable scale for experienced well-being (people’s evaluations of their lives) and evaluative well-being (how people feel during the day-to-day moments of their lives).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>They included a large number of high-earning participants and measured higher incomes in more granular increments.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The data were collected from 33,391 employed adults (ages 18-65) in the United States. There were a total of 1,725,994 reports collected, so that&amp;rsquo;s ~52 reports per person.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>quotes from a Lex Fridman interview with Philip Goff</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/philip-goff/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 09:39:16 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/philip-goff/</guid><description>&lt;p>Here are some snippets from a Lex Fridman &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20221222002116/https://lexfridman.com/philip-goff/">interview&lt;/a> with Philip Goff, a panpsychist.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The Enlightenment ideal is to follow the evidence and the arguments where they lead, but it&amp;rsquo;s very hard for human beings to do that. I think we get stuck in some conception of how we think science ought to look. People talk about religion as a crutch, but I think a certain kind of scientism, a certain conception of how science is supposed to be, gets into people&amp;rsquo;s identity and their sense of themselves and their security.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Educated</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/educated/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2022 09:51:11 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/educated/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="thinking-for-yourself">thinking for yourself &lt;a class="header-link" href="#thinking-for-yourself">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I recognized myself a little in this book, not in the events, severity, or locations but in the path to being &amp;ldquo;educated&amp;rdquo; in the sense that Westover intends. I&amp;rsquo;ll try to convey what that sense is with some quotes from the book.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first moment is after she takes a class on American history at BYU. She returns home and gets her face dirty while working, and her brother calls her a N&amp;mdash;r, a joke he had made many times before.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>meaning-making in the post-modern world</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/meaning-making/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 14:35:37 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/meaning-making/</guid><description>&lt;p>Here are some snippets from a Lex Fridman &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20221227111818/https://lexfridman.com/peter-wang/">interview&lt;/a> with Peter Wang, co-founder and CEO of Anaconda:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>For a lot of human history, there wasn&amp;rsquo;t so much a meaning crisis as just a food and not getting eaten by bears crisis. Once you get to a point where you can make food there was a not getting killed by other humans crisis. Sitting around wondering what it&amp;rsquo;s all about is a relatively recent luxury.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Cratylus</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/cratylus/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Jan 2022 15:11:14 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/cratylus/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this dialog Hermogenes comes to Socrates to discuss Cratylus&amp;rsquo; view of the nature of names, whether they are true to the objects they represent or are just conventional. Hermogenes believes that names are purely conventional, while Cratylus believes the opposite. Socrates falls somewhere in the middle:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I quite agree with you that words should as far as possible resemble things; but I fear that this dragging in of resemblance, as Hermogenes says, is a shabby thing, which has to be supplemented by the mechanical aid of convention with a view to correctness; for I believe that if we could always, or almost always, use likenesses, which are perfectly appropriate, this would be the most perfect state of language; as the opposite is the most imperfect.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Crito</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/crito/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Dec 2021 14:05:02 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/crito/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this dialogue Crito comes to Socrates who is in prison waiting to be executed by the state. Crito has come to convince Socrates to come and escape with him. Crito&amp;rsquo;s escape plan will not cause great inconvenience for any of Socrates&amp;rsquo; friends, and he would be able to live well in Thessaly. Socrates ends up convincing Crito that it would be wrong for him to escape.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-opinion-of-the-many">&amp;ldquo;the opinion of the many&amp;rdquo; &lt;a class="header-link" href="#the-opinion-of-the-many">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>CRITO: But you see, Socrates, that the opinion of the many must be regarded, for what is now happening shows that they can do the greatest evil to anyone who has lost their good opinion.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Apology of Socrates</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/apology/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 13:40:45 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/apology/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m starting a course of foundational texts in philosophy with a friend of mine, and this is the first one we&amp;rsquo;ve read. Socrates is often considered a founder of Western philosophy, and it was easy for me to see in the text some common philosophical themes I&amp;rsquo;ve been exposed to growing up in the West.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-fear-of-death-is-irrational">the fear of death is irrational &lt;a class="header-link" href="#the-fear-of-death-is-irrational">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Socrates argues that the fear of death is irrational from two perspectives: one, that what happens after death cannot be bad; and two, that a righteous person needs to be more concerned with whether he is doing right or wrong than whether death occurs or not. You can see the first one here:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Essentialism</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/essentialism/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2020 07:47:12 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/essentialism/</guid><description>&lt;p>The main character of the first story slowly changed his attitude toward demands on his resources.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Can I actually fulfill this request, given the time and resources I have?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Is this the very most important thing I should be doing with my time and resources right now?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Just because I was invited didn&amp;rsquo;t seem a good enough reason to attend.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s important to pursue &amp;ldquo;less but better&amp;rdquo; in a disciplined way. Simply doing fewer things is not meaningful. Most things in the world are trivial noise, and my job is to sift through noise and find things that are truly valuable. This involves active consideration of responsibilities and trade-offs involved in making a choice. I think I often try to &amp;ldquo;force execution at the last moment&amp;rdquo;, which is a mark of a non-essentialist.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>