<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Machine-Learning on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/tags/machine-learning/</link><description>Recent content in Machine-Learning on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 13:19:47 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/tags/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>the NYT AI explainer misses the point</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/nyt-ai-explainer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2023 10:07:35 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/nyt-ai-explainer/</guid><description>&lt;p>In late March 2023, the NYT released a series of explainer articles about AI. The &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/article/ai-artificial-intelligence-chatbot.html">first article in the series&lt;/a>&lt;span class="sidenote-number">&lt;small class="sidenote">You can also &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20230415130643/https://www.nytimes.com/article/ai-artificial-intelligence-chatbot.html">read it on Archive.org&lt;/a> if you don&amp;rsquo;t have a subscription.&lt;/small>&lt;/span>
characterizes the recent history of AI as a progression of new technological ideas appearing over time. Of course that&amp;rsquo;s partially true, but it gets the order wrong and misses important non-technical events that are key to understanding our current position.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>for a socially beneficial and responsible development of AI</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/bengio-crawford/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 14:04:51 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/bengio-crawford/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>These are my notes from a conversation between &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yoshua_Bengio">Yoshua Bengio&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kate_Crawford">Kate Crawford&lt;/a> held at &lt;a href="https://mila.quebec/">Mila&lt;/a> on 2023-03-20, announcing the release of a new book created as a joint report between Mila and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UNESCO">UNESCO&lt;/a> called&lt;/em> Missing links in AI governance &lt;em>(&lt;a href="https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000384787">link&lt;/a>). There were news articles in French (&lt;a href="https://www.ledevoir.com/societe/785960/intelligence-artificielle-l-onu-et-le-mila-inquiets-des-derapages-potentiels-d-ia-comme-chatgpt">Le Devoir&lt;/a>), but not as many in English unfortunately (&lt;a href="https://www.datanami.com/this-just-in/mila-and-unesco-join-forces-to-emphasize-urgent-need-for-better-ai-governance/">Datanami&lt;/a>).&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Bengio&lt;/strong>: What motivates you to do what you do? This topic has turned from an academic move to a societal one really quickly, and it&amp;rsquo;s scary. We need to figure out what to do.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>WordBurner beta</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/wordburner/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2022 23:08:52 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/wordburner/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Update 2022-04-27&lt;/strong>: The beta is over, but the apk is still installable with the instructions below and any feedback sent from inside the app will be received by me. I&amp;rsquo;m going to be working on this more over the summer, and eventually publishing it on the app store. :)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ever since learning Spanish, it has been a dream of mine to create a vocabulary study app that meets my needs. Duolingo won&amp;rsquo;t cover advanced vocabulary, Anki requires manually-generated decks, and other apps have expensive subscription plans.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Jupyter Lab Hub in Docker with Nvidia GPU support</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/jupyter-lab/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 20:28:25 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/jupyter-lab/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is how I set up my headless home server with a Jupyter Lab Docker container with an Nvidia GPU runtime. Login is handled by a GitHub OAuth application.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="nvidia-drivers-and-the-container-runtime">Nvidia drivers and the container runtime &lt;a class="header-link" href="#nvidia-drivers-and-the-container-runtime">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>First, check &lt;a href="https://docs.nvidia.com/cuda/archive/11.4.2/cuda-toolkit-release-notes/index.html">here&lt;/a> (replacing the CUDA version in the URL with your own) to see which Nvidia drivers you need for the CUDA toolkit version you want. I&amp;rsquo;m using CUDA 11.4.2, which means I need at least driver version 470.&lt;span class="sidenote-number">&lt;small class="sidenote">You can use &lt;code>sudo apt purge nvidia-*&lt;/code> to cleanly remove older drivers (or broken installs) before installing the desired version.&lt;/small>&lt;/span>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>