<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Canada on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/tags/canada/</link><description>Recent content in Canada on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 12:37:51 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/tags/canada/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>learning French</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/learning-french/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 12:19:08 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/learning-french/</guid><description>&lt;p>Here I&amp;rsquo;m going to document my efforts to learn French. I speak Spanish pretty well, which together with English gives me a strong base for comprehension.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>2021-08-01&lt;/strong>: I started using Duolingo every day, and got into the XP challenges to the point where I was getting like hundreds of points most days. I&amp;rsquo;ve currently (2022-06-01) got 15821 XP and 103 lesson crowns in the French course, and most of that came from Fall 2021. That really gave me a good sense for basic grammar and function words.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>moving to Québec</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/qu%C3%A9bec/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 11:55:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/qu%C3%A9bec/</guid><description>&lt;p>We just moved our family from Utah, USA, to Montréal, Québec, Canada. I entered Canada on August 18, 2021 &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/maps/dir/Salt+Lake+City,+UT/montreal/@42.7334015,-101.7162703,5z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m13!4m12!1m5!1m1!1s0x87523d9488d131ed:0x5b53b7a0484d31ca!2m2!1d-111.8910474!2d40.7607793!1m5!1m1!1s0x4cc91a541c64b70d:0x654e3138211fefef!2m2!1d-73.567256!2d45.5016889">by car&lt;/a>, and my wife and daughter entered a few days later by air. The process actually began on April 27 when I got my acceptance letter to the Université de Montréal as a master&amp;rsquo;s student in the &lt;a href="https://diro.umontreal.ca/accueil/">Département d&amp;rsquo;informatique et de recherche opérationelle&lt;/a>. After a few days of scrambling to find out if I would be able to study there without knowing French (turns out you can as a grad student at DIRO!), I started the process of applying to enter Canada and live in Québec as a student.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>