<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Religion on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/tags/religion/</link><description>Recent content in Religion on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 16:26:59 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/tags/religion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Educated</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/educated/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2022 09:51:11 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/educated/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="thinking-for-yourself">thinking for yourself &lt;a class="header-link" href="#thinking-for-yourself">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I recognized myself a little in this book, not in the events, severity, or locations but in the path to being &amp;ldquo;educated&amp;rdquo; in the sense that Westover intends. I&amp;rsquo;ll try to convey what that sense is with some quotes from the book.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first moment is after she takes a class on American history at BYU. She returns home and gets her face dirty while working, and her brother calls her a N&amp;mdash;r, a joke he had made many times before.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Planted: belief and belonging in an age of doubt</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/planted/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2021 10:21:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/planted/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>(My own thoughts appear as sidenotes or in italics, to distinguish from the author&amp;rsquo;s thoughts.)&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Richard Bushman categorizes those who leave the church into two broad categories: those who feel &amp;ldquo;switched off&amp;rdquo;, and those who feel &amp;ldquo;squeezed out&amp;rdquo;. Mason summarizes the switched-off group as those who encounter troubling information about church history or doctrine, and as they discover more information they become jaded by it until they can no longer see the good the church does for them or for others. The squeezed-out group &amp;ldquo;fully embrace[s] the basic principles and ordinances of the gospel. But sometimes they feel alienated by things like the dominant political conservatism among the members &amp;hellip; or how the church ministers to our LGBT &amp;hellip; brothers and sisters,&amp;rdquo; (p. 3).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The infinite Atonement</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/infinite-atonement/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Mar 2021 06:30:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/infinite-atonement/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>These notes are made while reading this with a Mormon theological background, so I skip noting some of the basic Mormon doctrines about the Atonement that he teaches.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Atonement is the central doctrine of Christianity. All scripture should be at least partially focused on it, and we&amp;rsquo;re invited to &amp;ldquo;speak of the atonement of Christ, and attain to a perfect knowledge of him&amp;rdquo; (Jacob 4:12).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-the-significance-of-the-atonement">What is the significance of the Atonement? &lt;a class="header-link" href="#what-is-the-significance-of-the-atonement">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Here are some of the ways that we come to understand the Atonement:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Faith is not blind</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/faith-is-not-blind/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 08:11:23 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/faith-is-not-blind/</guid><description>&lt;p>Elder Hafen struggled as a missionary with the concept of knowing versus believing: he felt he believed it was true, but not that he knew it. On the mission he felt pressure to bear testimony with the word &amp;ldquo;know&amp;rdquo;, but he chafed at that. In this book, Elder Hafen hopes to discuss the complex boundaries between believing and knowing, Richard Bushman, a prominent LDS historian, found himself in a similar situation. He felt that he didn&amp;rsquo;t have the right words to express his belief in the nuanced way that he needed, even though looking back he thinks he &lt;em>did&lt;/em> believe. This makes me look forward to reading Bushman&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Rough Stone Rolling&amp;rdquo;, to try to understand his language of faith.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The faith of a scientist</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/faith-of-a-scientist/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 06:46:49 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/faith-of-a-scientist/</guid><description>&lt;p>Scientific thinking and religion go hand in hand, and help refine and give purpose to each other.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Descartes&amp;rsquo; approach wasn&amp;rsquo;t as good as Newton&amp;rsquo;s. Descartes relied on the soundness of his own reasoning.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;The erroneous conception that revelation ended with the apostles promotes the misconception among sectarian religions that the Gospel is complete and that with a liberal admixture of human wisdom, all will be crystal clear.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>God places messages in everything. We study the scriptures, but we also study each scientific field looking for the truth He offers us there.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Increase in learning: spiritual patterns for obtaining your own answers</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/increase-in-learning/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 10:14:43 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/increase-in-learning/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="chapter-1">Chapter 1 &lt;a class="header-link" href="#chapter-1">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We are give the opportunity to have the Spirit as a &lt;em>constant&lt;/em> companion! To take advantage, we need to sincerely desire it, invite it through action, and be worthy of it through obedience.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="chapter-2">Chapter 2 &lt;a class="header-link" href="#chapter-2">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Knowledge&lt;/strong> is the accumulation of facts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Understanding&lt;/strong> comes when we apply our hearts to knowledge, which lets the Holy Ghost testify to us of the truthfulness of it. Understanding comes by revelation.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>