<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Economics on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/tags/economics/</link><description>Recent content in Economics on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 15:54:58 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/tags/economics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>thoughts on technology ownership</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/tech-ownership/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2023 12:11:06 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/tech-ownership/</guid><description>&lt;p>Having heard about the &lt;a href="https://foundation.mozilla.org/en/privacynotincluded/articles/its-official-cars-are-the-worst-product-category-we-have-ever-reviewed-for-privacy/">terrible privacy policies of car manufacturers&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/3/3/23624328/ford-self-repossessing-car-patent-connected-car-nightmare">Ford&amp;rsquo;s new patent to automate vehicle repossession&lt;/a>, I was finally able to formulate some thoughts I&amp;rsquo;ve had brewing for a while about ownership in this world of ubiquitous computing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Before the industrial revolution, humans could essentially understand what a thing did by looking at it, and ownership was about possession of the object. Now we don&amp;rsquo;t understand our tools, and so possession does not imply control.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Winners take all: the elite charade of changing the world</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/winners-take-all/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 14:48:27 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/winners-take-all/</guid><description>&lt;p>This book was a good one for quotable critique of modern capitalism. Here are some good ones:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>These elites believe and promote the idea that social change should be pursued principally through the free market and voluntary action, not public life and the law and the reform of the systems that people share in common; that it should be supervised by the winners of capitalism and their allies, and not be antagonistic to their needs; and that the biggest beneficiaries of the status quo should play a leading role in the status quo’s reform.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The big three in economics: Adam Smith, Karl Marx, and John Maynard Keynes</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/big-three-economics/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 13:28:01 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/big-three-economics/</guid><description>&lt;p>This book was published in 2007, before the Great Recession. It definitely reads that way. Very capitalist, very Christian, very neo-liberal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I enjoyed learning more about Adam Smith. I feel like Skousen does a good job painting the importance of his ideas as an invention that drove the Industrial Revolution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to Skousen, Marx is the devil incarnate, and his ideas are a dangerous disease infecting the minds of intellectuals and workers. Skousen takes a strange interest in painting Marx and Keynes as deranged, sexual deviants, etc. (&amp;ldquo;The Truth about Keynes&amp;rsquo; Homosexuality&amp;rdquo; is a section in this book.)&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>