<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Sociology on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/tags/sociology/</link><description>Recent content in Sociology on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2024 16:49:59 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/tags/sociology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Bowling alone: the collapse and revival of American community</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/bowling-alone/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 10:36:57 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/bowling-alone/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-trends">the trends &lt;a class="header-link" href="#the-trends">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>politics&lt;/strong>: There is now more money in politics, and less individual involvement. There are more total associations, but they look more like the AARP and Greenpeace, instead of unions, churches, bridge clubs, rotary.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>religion&lt;/strong>: Attendance has definitely gone down in the last 40 years, even if the number of people who profess stays nearly the same. (This has changed since the book was published on January 1, 2000.) The 60s and 70s saw people make their religion more private, more personal, making people less concerned with the communal support of a shared faith. Fundamentalist religion (including evangelical) results in more service and giving, but primarily within the church community. So as the mainline middle falls out, religion is becoming a less helpful societal lubricant overall, despite the fact that religiosity has generally meant more volunteerism and giving.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>ethics drift within bubbles</title><link>https://kylrth.com/post/ethics-drift/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 08:35:54 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/post/ethics-drift/</guid><description>&lt;p>Here are some snippets from a Lex Fridman &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20221222002108/https://lexfridman.com/john-abramson/">interview&lt;/a> with John Abramson, outspoken critic of Big Pharma.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Lex&lt;/strong>: Are people corrupt? Are people malevolent? Are people ignorant that work at the low level and at the high level, at Pfizer for example? How is this possible? I believe that most people are good, and I actually believe if you join Big Pharma your life trajectory often involves dreaming, wanting, and enjoying helping people. And then we look at the outcomes that you&amp;rsquo;re describing and that&amp;rsquo;s why the narrative takes hold that Pfizer CEO Albert Bourla is malevolent. The sense is that these companies are evil. So if the different parts are people that are good and they want to do good, how are we getting these outcomes?&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>