<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Rationality on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/tags/rationality/</link><description>Recent content in Rationality on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 13:19:47 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/tags/rationality/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Think again: the power of knowing what you don't know</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/think-again/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 15:08:24 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/think-again/</guid><description>&lt;p>The book is divided into 3 parts, covering the value of rethinking, how to help others rethink, and how to help communities rethink.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-value-of-rethinking">the value of rethinking &lt;a class="header-link" href="#the-value-of-rethinking">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Who you are should be a question of what you value, not what you believe.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When people change their answers on a test, they&amp;rsquo;re far more likely to change to the right answer than a wrong answer. Rethinking is effective!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="helping-others-rethink">helping others rethink &lt;a class="header-link" href="#helping-others-rethink">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Good families allow for healthy conflict, rather than avoiding it. Orville and Wilbur Wright fought a lot but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t relational conflict, it was task conflict. Having a good relationship with colleagues is important because it&amp;rsquo;s what keeps task conflict from bleeding into relational conflict. You need a network of people who will disagree with you. Silence disrespects the value of your views, and our ability to have civil disagreement.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The drunkard's walk: how randomness rules our lives</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/drunkards-walk/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 13:23:22 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/drunkards-walk/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a good intro for non-statisticians to avoid some common pitfalls and misconceptions that the public often has. It&amp;rsquo;ll help you understand what it means when something is statistically significant, why sometimes studies contradict each other, and how to avoid believing in patterns that don&amp;rsquo;t exist. You&amp;rsquo;ll understand the following biases and fallacies:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>confirmation bias&lt;/li>
&lt;li>gambler&amp;rsquo;s fallacy&lt;/li>
&lt;li>hot hand fallacy&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;hindsight is 20/20&amp;rdquo;: the illusion of hindsight for explaining historical performance/events&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>One mistake I want to point out:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Harry Potter and the methods of rationality</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/hpmor/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 07:25:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/hpmor/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>&lt;strong>Spoiler warning: no plot held back in this review.&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="science-is-at-least-as-beautiful-as-magic">science is at least as beautiful as magic &lt;a class="header-link" href="#science-is-at-least-as-beautiful-as-magic">&lt;svg class="c-links__icon">&lt;title>permalink&lt;/title>&lt;use xlink:href="#icon-permalink">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In chapter 7 Harry introduces Draco to the beauty of scientific advancement, and it actually moved me to tears. You should read the &lt;a href="https://www.hpmor.com/chapter/7">whole thing&lt;/a>, but here are some of the best quotes:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Anyway,&amp;rdquo; Harry said, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m saying that you don&amp;rsquo;t seem to have been paying much attention to what goes on in the Muggle world.&amp;rdquo; Probably because the whole wizarding world seemed to regard the rest of Earth as a slum, deserving around as much news coverage as the Financial Times awarded to the routine agonies of Burundi. &amp;ldquo;All right. Quick check. Have wizards ever been to the Moon? You know, that thing?&amp;rdquo; Harry pointed up to that huge and distant globe.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>