<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Rationality on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/tags/rationality/</link><description>Recent content in Rationality on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 16:25:25 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/tags/rationality/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Think again: the power of knowing what you don't know</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/think-again/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 15:08:24 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/think-again/</guid><description>The book is divided into 3 parts, covering the value of rethinking, how to help others rethink, and how to help communities rethink.
the value of rethinking permalink Who you are should be a question of what you value, not what you believe.
When people change their answers on a test, they&amp;rsquo;re far more likely to change to the right answer than a wrong answer. Rethinking is effective!
helping others rethink permalink Good families allow for healthy conflict, rather than avoiding it.</description></item><item><title>The drunkard's walk: how randomness rules our lives</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/drunkards-walk/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 13:23:22 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/drunkards-walk/</guid><description>This is a good intro for non-statisticians to avoid some common pitfalls and misconceptions that the public often has. It&amp;rsquo;ll help you understand what it means when something is statistically significant, why sometimes studies contradict each other, and how to avoid believing in patterns that don&amp;rsquo;t exist. You&amp;rsquo;ll understand the following biases and fallacies:
confirmation bias gambler&amp;rsquo;s fallacy hot hand fallacy &amp;ldquo;hindsight is 20/20&amp;rdquo;: the illusion of hindsight for explaining historical performance/events One mistake I want to point out:</description></item><item><title>Harry Potter and the methods of rationality</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/hpmor/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 07:25:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/hpmor/</guid><description>Spoiler warning: no plot held back in this review.
science is at least as beautiful as magic permalink In chapter 7 Harry introduces Draco to the beauty of scientific advancement, and it actually moved me to tears. You should read the whole thing, but here are some of the best quotes:
&amp;ldquo;Anyway,&amp;rdquo; Harry said, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m saying that you don&amp;rsquo;t seem to have been paying much attention to what goes on in the Muggle world.</description></item></channel></rss>