<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>books on Kyle Roth</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/</link><description>Recent content in books on Kyle Roth</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://kylrth.com/book/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The right side of history: how reason and moral purpose made the West great</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/right-side-of-history/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 13:36:03 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/right-side-of-history/</guid><description>The main text below is my summary of the points in the book, and I&amp;rsquo;ve put my commentary in sidenotes. If you want a Marxist, postmodern response to these ideas from the devil himself, check out Jordan Peterson &amp;amp; the meaning of life by Philosophy Tube.
Reason and moral purpose come from Athens and Jerusalem, and without those things the West would not be where it is today. Socialism means taking handouts from the nanny state, and while our society continues to function with capitalism bearing the weight of socialist programs, it&amp;rsquo;s in the process of crumbling.</description></item><item><title>Killing sacred cows: overcoming the financial myths that are destroying your prosperity</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/killing-sacred-cows/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 13:06:34 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/killing-sacred-cows/</guid><description>This book made me cringe pretty often. I&amp;rsquo;ll leave exclamation points (!) on particularly cringe-worthy ideas, just so you can see how based I am.
This book functions on the idea that if we accept a new set of words: poverty mindset, abundance mindset, etc, we&amp;rsquo;ll become wealthy.
Zero-sum mindset: any critique of &amp;ldquo;success&amp;rdquo;, including environmental devastation Scarcity/poverty mindset: saving your way to wealth, judging or being jealous of those who have things, being too safe or too risky with your money, avoiding the risk of seeking your dreams, any ideas that make you make bad decisions If more people live with an abundance mindset, we will all experience less hardship.</description></item><item><title>Raising an emotionally intelligent child: the heart of parenting</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/raising-emotionally-intelligent-child/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 12:57:20 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/raising-emotionally-intelligent-child/</guid><description>Really fantastic book. Here is a quote that was extremely key for me:
Understand your base of power as a parent. By base of power, I mean the element in the parent-child relationship that makes it possible for parents to set limits on children&amp;rsquo;s misbehavior, something all kids want and need. For some parents, the base of power is threats, humiliation, or spanking. Others, who are overly permissive, may feel they have no base of power at all.</description></item><item><title>Why we sleep: unlocking the power of sleep and dreams</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/why-we-sleep/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2023 22:00:32 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/why-we-sleep/</guid><description>There is controversy around some of the claims made in this book, so I don&amp;rsquo;t take any single point of evidence extremely seriously. But the person who critiqued the book also has some weird ideas about sleep,For instance, he believes that we evolved in a sleep-deprived environment so sleep deprivation must be healthier for us. so in the end I think I probably side with the sleep scientist for most issues except when he seems extreme.</description></item><item><title>Winners take all: the elite charade of changing the world</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/winners-take-all/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 14:48:27 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/winners-take-all/</guid><description>This book was a good one for quotable critique of modern capitalism. Here are some good ones:
These elites believe and promote the idea that social change should be pursued principally through the free market and voluntary action, not public life and the law and the reform of the systems that people share in common; that it should be supervised by the winners of capitalism and their allies, and not be antagonistic to their needs; and that the biggest beneficiaries of the status quo should play a leading role in the status quo’s reform.</description></item><item><title>Think again: the power of knowing what you don't know</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/think-again/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 15:08:24 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/think-again/</guid><description>The book is divided into 3 parts, covering the value of rethinking, how to help others rethink, and how to help communities rethink.
the value of rethinking permalink Who you are should be a question of what you value, not what you believe.
When people change their answers on a test, they&amp;rsquo;re far more likely to change to the right answer than a wrong answer. Rethinking is effective!
helping others rethink permalink Good families allow for healthy conflict, rather than avoiding it.</description></item><item><title>Army of none: autonomous weapons and the future of war</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/army-of-none/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 13:33:19 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/army-of-none/</guid><description>The examples in this book make it clear that there is no easy line we can draw between autonomous and non-autonomous weapons (and by extension, autonomous AI agents). There is a smooth gradient of autonomy, which makes the question of allowing autonomous weapons much more nuanced. It&amp;rsquo;s probably the case that higher-level alignment becomes important proportionally to the level of autonomy and intelligence.
He analyzes the Patriot fratricides,In a military context, the word fratricide means the killing of someone on the same side of a conflict.</description></item><item><title>Conscious: a brief guide to the fundamental mystery of the mind</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/conscious/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 16:57:49 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/conscious/</guid><description>The first thing you should know is that this book is only 2 hours long in audio form. That&amp;rsquo;s short! She managed to get into the difficult details while keeping the jargon accessible. (It helps that we literally know nothing about consciousness.)
This book argued alternately for neuroscientific, illusionist, and panpsychist theories of consciousness. It explains the hard problem of consciousness, and then later really explains why it&amp;rsquo;s so hard. As a science-oriented person, t&amp;rsquo;s so easy to forget why it&amp;rsquo;s hard and start to explain things purely physically.</description></item><item><title>Being mortal: medicine and what matters in the end</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/being-mortal/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 09:04:11 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/being-mortal/</guid><description>Read this book before you turn 60. In fact, read it before you&amp;rsquo;re 40. Read it before your parents are 60. Read it if you have parents! Read it if you&amp;rsquo;re a person who is likely to die sometime in the future.
This book gave me tools for the hard decisions that exist for people in the last decade(s) of their lives. Before reaching this stage of life ourselves, we don&amp;rsquo;t think about it much because we&amp;rsquo;ve tended to separate the aged from our communities.</description></item><item><title>The big three in economics: Adam Smith, Karl Marx, and John Maynard Keynes</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/big-three-economics/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 13:28:01 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/big-three-economics/</guid><description>This book was published in 2007, before the Great Recession. It definitely reads that way. Very capitalist, very Christian, very neo-liberal.
I enjoyed learning more about Adam Smith. I feel like Skousen does a good job painting the importance of his ideas as an invention that drove the Industrial Revolution.
According to Skousen, Marx is the devil incarnate, and his ideas are a dangerous disease infecting the minds of intellectuals and workers.</description></item><item><title>The drunkard's walk: how randomness rules our lives</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/drunkards-walk/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 13:23:22 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/drunkards-walk/</guid><description>This is a good intro for non-statisticians to avoid some common pitfalls and misconceptions that the public often has. It&amp;rsquo;ll help you understand what it means when something is statistically significant, why sometimes studies contradict each other, and how to avoid believing in patterns that don&amp;rsquo;t exist. You&amp;rsquo;ll understand the following biases and fallacies:
confirmation bias gambler&amp;rsquo;s fallacy hot hand fallacy &amp;ldquo;hindsight is 20/20&amp;rdquo;: the illusion of hindsight for explaining historical performance/events One mistake I want to point out:</description></item><item><title>The birth order book: why you are the way you are</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/birth-order/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 09:48:05 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/birth-order/</guid><description>This book really gave me the chance to think about what being the firstborn did to my personality and my life outlook. I think it&amp;rsquo;s pretty clear I fit the mold of a perfectionist firstborn, thanks to having usually met the high expectations of my parents growing up. It&amp;rsquo;s been especially valuable to think about how that will affect my own parenting, especially toward my first child. I think one of the most useful things about the book is that it prepares a parent to try to mediate some of the negative consequences of birth order.</description></item><item><title>Educated</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/educated/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2022 09:51:11 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/educated/</guid><description>thinking for yourself permalink I recognized myself a little in this book, not in the events, severity, or locations but in the path to being &amp;ldquo;educated&amp;rdquo; in the sense that Westover intends. I&amp;rsquo;ll try to convey what that sense is with some quotes from the book.
The first moment is after she takes a class on American history at BYU. She returns home and gets her face dirty while working, and her brother calls her a N&amp;mdash;r, a joke he had made many times before.</description></item><item><title>Cratylus</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/cratylus/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Jan 2022 15:11:14 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/cratylus/</guid><description>In this dialog Hermogenes comes to Socrates to discuss Cratylus&amp;rsquo; view of the nature of names, whether they are true to the objects they represent or are just conventional. Hermogenes believes that names are purely conventional, while Cratylus believes the opposite. Socrates falls somewhere in the middle:
I quite agree with you that words should as far as possible resemble things; but I fear that this dragging in of resemblance, as Hermogenes says, is a shabby thing, which has to be supplemented by the mechanical aid of convention with a view to correctness; for I believe that if we could always, or almost always, use likenesses, which are perfectly appropriate, this would be the most perfect state of language; as the opposite is the most imperfect.</description></item><item><title>Crito</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/crito/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Dec 2021 14:05:02 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/crito/</guid><description>In this dialogue Crito comes to Socrates who is in prison waiting to be executed by the state. Crito has come to convince Socrates to come and escape with him. Crito&amp;rsquo;s escape plan will not cause great inconvenience for any of Socrates&amp;rsquo; friends, and he would be able to live well in Thessaly. Socrates ends up convincing Crito that it would be wrong for him to escape.
&amp;ldquo;the opinion of the many&amp;rdquo; permalink CRITO: But you see, Socrates, that the opinion of the many must be regarded, for what is now happening shows that they can do the greatest evil to anyone who has lost their good opinion.</description></item><item><title>Apology of Socrates</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/apology/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 13:40:45 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/apology/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m starting a course of foundational texts in philosophy with a friend of mine, and this is the first one we&amp;rsquo;ve read. Socrates is often considered a founder of Western philosophy, and it was easy for me to see in the text some common philosophical themes I&amp;rsquo;ve been exposed to growing up in the West.
the fear of death is irrational permalink Socrates argues that the fear of death is irrational from two perspectives: one, that what happens after death cannot be bad; and two, that a righteous person needs to be more concerned with whether he is doing right or wrong than whether death occurs or not.</description></item><item><title>The last speakers: the quest to save the world's most endangered languages</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/last-speakers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 May 2021 08:29:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/last-speakers/</guid><description>This book argues that language loss is always bad, but that we can do something to save it. While the stories in the book leave me feeling like every language lost is a terrible cost, I think it&amp;rsquo;s inevitable as our species merges into a global society due to technology. I think we ought to prioritize the proper treatment and respect of marginalized and alternative cultures, including their languages and how these cultures want to maintain them.</description></item><item><title>The seven principles for making marriage work: a practical guide from the country's foremost relationship expert</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/seven-principles-for-marriage/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 06:52:44 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/seven-principles-for-marriage/</guid><description>Better communication doesn&amp;rsquo;t really solve marriage problems. It has a low success rate, and that makes sense because there are plenty of marriages that yell and dispute. Disputation is not a sign of an unhealthy marriage. You&amp;rsquo;d have to be really magnanimous to take criticism about you, even if presented as softly as possible.
Personality does not make a marriage incompatible. People can be friends but have very distinct personalities. Handle each other&amp;rsquo;s strange side with caring and respect, as you would a friend.</description></item><item><title>Harry Potter and the methods of rationality</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/hpmor/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 07:25:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/hpmor/</guid><description>Spoiler warning: no plot held back in this review.
science is at least as beautiful as magic permalink In chapter 7 Harry introduces Draco to the beauty of scientific advancement, and it actually moved me to tears. You should read the whole thing, but here are some of the best quotes:
&amp;ldquo;Anyway,&amp;rdquo; Harry said, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m saying that you don&amp;rsquo;t seem to have been paying much attention to what goes on in the Muggle world.</description></item><item><title>Planted: belief and belonging in an age of doubt</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/planted/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2021 10:21:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/planted/</guid><description>(My own thoughts appear as sidenotes or in italics, to distinguish from the author&amp;rsquo;s thoughts.)
Richard Bushman categorizes those who leave the church into two broad categories: those who feel &amp;ldquo;switched off&amp;rdquo;, and those who feel &amp;ldquo;squeezed out&amp;rdquo;. Mason summarizes the switched-off group as those who encounter troubling information about church history or doctrine, and as they discover more information they become jaded by it until they can no longer see the good the church does for them or for others.</description></item><item><title>The life-changing magic of tidying up: the Japanese art of decluttering and organizing</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/life-changing-magic/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 21:21:04 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/life-changing-magic/</guid><description>This book was my first real exposure to minimalism, and it completely changed how I feel about the possession of objects. It was super fortunate that my wife and I listened to it together on a road trip, and became equally enthralled with the idea of dumping all of our excess clutter.
all at once permalink We have excess clutter because of a fundamental problem with the way we deal with possessions.</description></item><item><title>The smartest kids in the world</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/smartest-kids/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Mar 2021 07:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/smartest-kids/</guid><description>The PISA test tests common senses reasoning. The countries that did best on the test were a surprise to everyone. Finland, South Korea, and Poland were all standouts in their own ways, and Ripley compares the policies and learning environments in these countries with those of the US to determine why the US is falling behind, especially in math and science.
We talk a lot about parent involvement in the US, but the US actually has above average parental involvement.</description></item><item><title>The infinite Atonement</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/infinite-atonement/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Mar 2021 06:30:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/infinite-atonement/</guid><description>These notes are made while reading this with a Mormon theological background, so I skip noting some of the basic Mormon doctrines about the Atonement that he teaches.
The Atonement is the central doctrine of Christianity. All scripture should be at least partially focused on it, and we&amp;rsquo;re invited to &amp;ldquo;speak of the atonement of Christ, and attain to a perfect knowledge of him&amp;rdquo; (Jacob 4:12).
What is the significance of the Atonement?</description></item><item><title>How not to diet: the groundbreaking science of healthy, permanent weight loss</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/how-not-to-diet/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 07:00:37 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/how-not-to-diet/</guid><description>I read this book with Irresistible and the Social Dilemma on my mind, so I have a lot of notes here about addiction and big business.
Just like everything else, capitalism has screwed over our diets by giving companies the incentive to put shareholders above customers. Food companies employ lobbyists to keep subsidies on sugar/corn syrup/meat, and keep a stranglehold on public organizations. They buy billions of dollars of ads to communicate the message that it&amp;rsquo;s laziness that has caused the obesity epidemic and to push their products that appeal to the unconscious desires of our brains to produce artificial hunger.</description></item><item><title>The gene: an intimate history</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/the-gene/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 06:14:58 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/the-gene/</guid><description>These are notes I made after finishing the book, so they&amp;rsquo;ll be more heavily weighted toward concepts discussed near the end. The first half of the book was primarily dedicated to a history of genetic research, which I think helped the reader understand the issues discussed in the latter half.
playing God permalink It seems like our identity derives from a complicated combination of genes and chance environmental effects. Part of our strength as a species has been our natural variation, and to begin editing the genome is to assume that we can do it better than evolution has done up until this point.</description></item><item><title>Faith is not blind</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/faith-is-not-blind/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 08:11:23 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/faith-is-not-blind/</guid><description>Elder Hafen struggled as a missionary with the concept of knowing versus believing: he felt he believed it was true, but not that he knew it. On the mission he felt pressure to bear testimony with the word &amp;ldquo;know&amp;rdquo;, but he chafed at that. In this book, Elder Hafen hopes to discuss the complex boundaries between believing and knowing, Richard Bushman, a prominent LDS historian, found himself in a similar situation.</description></item><item><title>Tools and weapons: the promise and peril of the digital age</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/tools-and-weapons/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 20:58:02 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/tools-and-weapons/</guid><description>I started taking notes later in the book. There were lots of good insights in the first half. Sorry!
broadband access permalink Getting the internet to rural communities is a big deal for the rural economy. Just like electricity, it&amp;rsquo;s something that needs government support because there isn&amp;rsquo;t the economic incentive for ISPs to reach some of these locations.
ethical AI permalink The focus on AI now is not just a fad, but a convergence of several trends that have made AI the next logical step: the increased computational resources, flexible access to compute through the cloud, etc.</description></item><item><title>Blink: the power of thinking without thinking</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/blink/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Nov 2020 20:44:48 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/blink/</guid><description>Our subconscious not only manages bodily systems but also performs processing of features in our experience that our conscious does not have time to process. This has been proven in lots of experiments where people have been given subconscious cues to help them solve problems, but the people are unaware of this and make up answers when asked to explain how they came to conclusions. It&amp;rsquo;s important to trust these judgments that seem to come out of nowhere, but if we try to explain them we&amp;rsquo;ll start trying to provide rational answers, which can be totally false or misleading.</description></item><item><title>A short history of nearly everything</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/short-history-nearly-everything/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2020 11:19:03 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/short-history-nearly-everything/</guid><description>We are extremely lucky to be here, and even more lucky to be able to appreciate it. Let&amp;rsquo;s not waste it.</description></item><item><title>The moment of lift: how empowering women changes the world</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/moment-of-lift/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 05:25:38 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/moment-of-lift/</guid><description>This book is about empowering women by giving them the freedom to make their own choices and speak for themselves. She said some important things about stigma in society. She talked specifically about the stigma of not talking about birth control, but she made general statements too. It&amp;rsquo;s each person&amp;rsquo;s responsibility to work against stigma and stop the human tendency to cast out others. I need to spend more time thinking about my own stigmas and biases, so that I can help those who are marginalized.</description></item><item><title>Naked economics: undressing the dismal science</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/naked-economics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 06:46:49 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/naked-economics/</guid><description>An important question is how much we need to fight income inequality. Is it fair to have 35% growth in the upper class and 3% growth in the lower class? Where is a good balance? We have grown a lot richer since the Industrial Revolution, because we&amp;rsquo;ve become more productive. Wealth is not a zero-sum game. Globalization is good because it allows us to buy cheaper, better products. We can offset short-run job loss by paying or giving human capital to those who lose their jobs to globalization Policies often don&amp;rsquo;t do what we intend them to do, because they change people&amp;rsquo;s decisions for the involved choice.</description></item><item><title>The faith of a scientist</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/faith-of-a-scientist/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 06:46:49 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/faith-of-a-scientist/</guid><description>Scientific thinking and religion go hand in hand, and help refine and give purpose to each other.
Descartes&amp;rsquo; approach wasn&amp;rsquo;t as good as Newton&amp;rsquo;s. Descartes relied on the soundness of his own reasoning.
&amp;ldquo;The erroneous conception that revelation ended with the apostles promotes the misconception among sectarian religions that the Gospel is complete and that with a liberal admixture of human wisdom, all will be crystal clear.&amp;rdquo;
God places messages in everything.</description></item><item><title>Weapons of math destruction: how big data increases inequality and threatens democracy</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/weapons-of-math-destruction/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 06:46:49 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/weapons-of-math-destruction/</guid><description>In fact, I saw all kinds of parallels between finance and Big Data. Both industries gobble up the same pool of talent, much of it from elite universities like MIT, Princeton, or Stanford. These new hires are ravenous for success and have been focused on external metrics&amp;ndash;like SAT scores and college admissions&amp;ndash;their entire lives. Whether in finance or tech, the message they&amp;rsquo;ve received is that they will be rich, that they will run the world.</description></item><item><title>Essentialism</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/essentialism/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2020 07:47:12 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/essentialism/</guid><description>The main character of the first story slowly changed his attitude toward demands on his resources.
&amp;ldquo;Can I actually fulfill this request, given the time and resources I have?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Is this the very most important thing I should be doing with my time and resources right now?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Just because I was invited didn&amp;rsquo;t seem a good enough reason to attend.&amp;rdquo; It&amp;rsquo;s important to pursue &amp;ldquo;less but better&amp;rdquo; in a disciplined way.</description></item><item><title>Increase in learning: spiritual patterns for obtaining your own answers</title><link>https://kylrth.com/book/increase-in-learning/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 10:14:43 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://kylrth.com/book/increase-in-learning/</guid><description>Chapter 1 permalink We are give the opportunity to have the Spirit as a constant companion! To take advantage, we need to sincerely desire it, invite it through action, and be worthy of it through obedience.
Chapter 2 permalink Knowledge is the accumulation of facts.
Understanding comes when we apply our hearts to knowledge, which lets the Holy Ghost testify to us of the truthfulness of it. Understanding comes by revelation.</description></item></channel></rss>